Finding Aid for Project on Asian Studies in Education (University of Michigan) records, 1972-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Project on Asian Studies in Education (University of Michigan) records 1972-1981
University of Michigan. Project on Asian Studies in Education.
2 linear feet
9435 Bimu 2
The Project on Asian Studies in Education (PASE) was established at the University of Michigan in 1971 as an outreach resource center to assist secondary and college-level instructors of Asian studies in developing curricula. Records include budget reports; minutes of the Project on Asian Studies in Education (PASE)'s Executive Committee meetings; correspondence, memoranda, and related materials pertaining to PASE's identification of funding agencies; grant proposals, reports, and related materials; job descriptions; memoranda pertaining to PASE's general office organization and prospective administrative reorganization; personnel records; bibliographies of Asia-related materials; conference/workshop materials; materials pertaining to PASE's development of curriculum units; newsletter samples; note cards of PASE's organizational and informational contacts; service request forms and letters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were transferred from the Project on Asian Studies in Education (Donor No. 8195 ) in November 1993.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open for research.
The Project on Asian Studies in Education (PASE) was established at the University of Michigan in August 1971. Earlier that year, a task force consisting of graduate students and faculty was formed to discuss ways in which the university's Center for Chinese Studies could extend its services to groups beyond its core scholarly users. The task force, headed by Ernest P. Young and Donald J. Munro, recommended that a Resource Center be established to assist secondary- and college-level teachers of Asian Studies in developing curricula. By April 1972, the Center for Japanese Studies and the Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies had joined the project.
Michael Fonte was appointed PASE's first coordinator. In 1976, Jo Ann (Jody) Hymes assumed the role of PASE coordinator/director. Hymes, the former outreach coordinator for the Center for Japanese Studies, ran the program with the director of each center and the executive committee. Susan Pratt Walton succeeded Hymes in 1978. That same year, the Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies (CSSEAS) assumed responsibility for PASE's funding. PASE was dissolved in 1981.
Housed in Lane Hall, PASE performed several activities. It developed and facilitated outreach programs on Asia for elementary- and secondary-school teachers and community groups. Through the Resource Center, it collected, evaluated, and produced materials pertaining to Asian cultures. Staff members created bibliographies and resource lists on these topics, as well as evaluated and published reviews of relevant audiovisual materials. It also operated a lending library through which it disseminated its audiovisual collection.
PASE provided in-service training opportunities to assist teachers at the elementary- and secondary-school level. Conferences, workshops, and extension-service courses were among the activities that the office developed to achieve this goal. Besides fulfilling community requests to design programs on specific countries or regions of Asia, PASE also consulted with school and community organizations on the local and national level to develop outreach programs. Members of the staff frequently gave presentations and held workshops at conferences on topics pertaining to Asia.
Records of the Project on Asian Studies in Education (PASE) date from 1972 to 1981 and measure 2 linear feet. The collection is divided into two series, Administrative Records and Outreach Activities, which document the project's activities within and outside the University.
Subjects:
Asia--Study and teaching.; Association for Asian Studies.; University of Michigan. Center for Chinese Studies.; University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies.; University of Michigan. Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies.; University of Michigan. Project on Asian Studies in Education.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records series is comprised of Budget Reports; Correspondence; Executive Committee Minutes; Funding Materials; Grant Proposals, Reports, and Related Materials; Job Descriptions; Memoranda; Office Organization; Preservation and Storage Concerns; Reorganization of PASE; Staff Meeting Notes; and Personnel Records.
  Highlights of this record group include five folders, which contain minutes of PASE's Executive Committee arranged chronologically. These records, dating from 1974 to August 1979, also include related correspondence and other materials that provide valuable information about the operation of the office.
  Five folders consisting of correspondence, memoranda, and other related materials document PASE's identification of funding agencies. This set of materials spans nearly the entire period of PASE's existence, although no materials from the years 1976 and 1979 are present. Complementing these records is a significant number of grant proposals, reports, and other related materials, which PASE submitted to various organizations in order to secure funding. It should be noted that two folders include proposals and related records sent to the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) during the years 1972 to 1975. To maintain these documents' original order, the folders are dated 1972-1975 and 1973-1975, respectively.
  The record group includes a folder of job postings and descriptions, which provide information about employees' responsibilities. Included also is one folder of memoranda exchanged between PASE and the Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies in 1975 and 1976. Of special note is a memo that serves as an introduction to PASE's recently reorganized personnel in 1976. Memoranda and correspondence from 1979 and 1980 document the prospective administrative reorganization of PASE.
  Because of the personally identifiable nature of the records contained, one folder of personnel-related documents is closed to research for thirty years past the records' dates of creation. These materials date from 1973 to 1980. The folder comprises the records of particular employees, arranged alphabetically by last name, which were selected for their documentation of PASE activities. Of special note are records pertaining to the three directors that PASE had throughout its existence.
  - Budget Reports 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes
    - 1974-June 1975 (Box 1)
    - July 1975-June 1976 (Box 1)
    - July 1976-June 1977 (Box 1)
    - July 1977-August 1978 (Box 1)
    - September 1978-August 1979 (Box 1)
  - Funding Materials
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Grant Proposals, Reports, and Related Materials
    - Michigan Council for the Arts 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Michigan Council for the Humanities, 1976/1977, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH)
      - 1972-1975 (Box 1)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 1)
    - NDEA
      - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
      - 1979/1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Job Descriptions (Box 1)
  - Memoranda (Box 1)
  - Office Organization (Box 1)
  - Preservation and Storage Concerns (Box 1)
  - Reorganization of PASE 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - South and Southeast Asian Studies, Center for 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Staff Meeting Notes 1978 (Box 1)
  - Personnel Records (selected employee records) 1976-1980, undated (Box 1)
- Outreach Activities
  Outreach Activities consist of twelve subseries: Association for Asian Studies (AAS); Bibliographies and Resource Lists; Citizen Education Amendment; Conference/Workshop Materials; Correspondence; Curriculum Development Units; Global Education Guidelines Committee; Newsletters; Organizational Contacts; Projects; Sample Forms; and Service Requests.
  Particularly noteworthy are two folders, which contain bibliographies of works on various Asian topics and resource lists of possible sources of Asia-related materials. These lists were compiled by PASE to assist teachers in selecting books and audiovisual materials for classroom use.
  Several folders contain conference and workshop materials, some of which reflect PASE's participation and others its sponsorship. Two folders are arranged chronologically and include materials pertaining to a small assortment of conferences and workshops. These workshops took place during the academic years 1973/1974 and 1977/1978. More substantial amounts of materials are present for other conferences and workshops, including the 1978 Arts of Asia conference and the 1976 Summer Workshop on Southeast Asia.
  The record group also includes a folder of correspondence dating from 1973 to 1978. Materials documenting PASE's development of curriculum units on subjects relating to such topics as Mahatma Gandhi, Asia in general, and South Asia, are included. The Gandhi material includes an audio cassette and corresponding script of the PASE program "Gandhi as Peacemaker," which once accompanied a filmstrip.
  Other significant materials in the record group include samples of the PASE newsletter, which are arranged chronologically, and a set of note cards bearing information on organizations and institutions that were considered to be important contacts to PASE. Materials on various projects sponsored by PASE, such as the Benefit Concert for Cambodian Refugees and the Indochinese Refugees Program, are arranged alphabetically by event.
  The subseries Service Requests contains forms and letters submitted to PASE by educators seeking primarily information on bibliographic and audiovisual materials. These materials are arranged in chronological files.
  - Association for Asian Studies (AAS)
    - Annual Convention 1977 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1975 (Box 2)
    - Indonesian Slide Project 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Bibliographies and Resource Lists, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Citizen Education Amendment (Box 2)
  - Conference/Workshop Materials
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Arts of Asia 1978 (Box 2)
    - Burton International School South Asia Curriculum Project (Box 2)
    - Conference on South Asia 1977 (Box 2)
    - Conference on Southeast Asia (Oberlin College) 1978 (Box 2)
    - Grand Rapids Project 1977 (Box 2)
    - Indochinese Refugee Education Conference 1980 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Conference on South and Southeast Asia 1980 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia Teachers' Workshop (Chicago Council on Foreign Relations) 1977 (Box 2)
    - Summer Workshop on Southeast Asia 1976 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1973-1978 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Development Units
    - Gandhi (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
    - South Asia (Box 2)
  - Global Education Guidelines Committee 1976 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters (Box 2)
  - Organizational Contacts (Box 2)
  - Projects
    - Benefit Concert for Cambodian Refugees 1980 (Box 2)
    - Indochinese Refugee Programs 1979 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Department of Education Social Studies Textbook Evaluation 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Prospective Project Materials 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - Sample Forms (Evaluations, Teaching Tools) (Box 2)
  - Service Requests
    - General Asian Materials
      - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - General East Asian Materials 1977 (Box 2)
    - PASE Requests to Outside Sources (Box 2)
    - South Asian Materials
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - South and Southeast Asian Materials 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asian Materials 1980-1981 (Box 2)
Related Material
Related record groups housed in the Bentley Library are those of the Center for Chinese Studies and the Center for Japanese Studies.